Guide to the Josephine Boardman Crane Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Josephine Boardman Crane papers
1912-1972
1926-1963
YCAL MSS 292
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8.13
(20 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, diaries, event files, and personal papers that document Josephine Boardman Crane's role as a socialite, patron, and philanthropist. These materials record Crane's daily activities, including a broad range of cultural events and numerous social contacts.
Crane, Josephine Boardman, 1873-1972
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Josephine Boardman Crane Estate, 1977.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Related material includes the Josephine Boardman Crane Papers Relating to the Dalton School, Uncat ZA MS 408, which contains material related to Crane's support of Helen Parkhurst's educational plan known as the Dalton plan and practiced at the Dalton School, New York, New York.
Josephine Boardman Crane
Josephine Boardman Crane was born November 1, 1873 in Cleveland, Ohio, the daughter of William Jarvis Boardman and Florence Sheffield. The family moved to Washington, D.C. where she met and, in 1906, married Winthrop Murray Crane, then United States Senator from Massachusetts. Between 1907 and 1917, Josephine and Winthrop Crane had three children: Stephen, Bruce, and Louise. Following her husband's death in 1920, Josephine Boardman Crane moved to New York City where she pursued philanthropic interests, serving as trustee for a number of cultural institutions including the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Museum of Modern Art, and the Morgan Library. Crane's interest in education led to her early support of Helen Parkhurst's Dalton plan and eventually of the Dalton School in New York. From the 1920s through the early 1960s, Crane hosted a range of cultural events, including musical performances, lectures, and literary gatherings that brought together performers, artists, and members of New York society. During this period she maintained extended relationships with the writers Padraic Colum, Marianne Moore, and Glenway Wescott. On July 9, 1972, Josephine Boardman Crane died at her home in Woods Hole, Massachusetts.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, diaries, event files, and personal papers that document Josephine Boardman Crane's role as a socialite, patron, and philanthropist. The correspondence dates from 1912 through Crane's death in July 1972 and is focused on cultural events hosted by Crane, with the bulk of the material dated from 1926-1963. Though there is limited personal material, the series includes significant correspondence with Padraic Colum, Marianne Moore, and Glenway Wescott documenting Crane's extended relationship with the three writers. The diaries provide a record of Crane's daily life from 1924 through 1963 when her eyesight worsened and she was unable to maintain the practice. Though she generally refrained from critical commentary, the diaries provide documentary evidence related to the cultural milieu in which Crane acted. Event files include a range of materials related to events hosted by Crane, such as guest lists, correspondence, menus, invitations, lecture notes and scripts. The limited personal papers incorporate miscellaneous materials including notebooks, clippings, travel arrangements, and related correspondence.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1912-1972. II. Diaries, 1926-1963. III. Event Files and Personal Papers, 1920-1964.
American literature -- 20th Century; Art patrons -- United States; Music patrons -- United States; Philanthropists -- United States; Women philanthropists -- United States; Colum, Padraic, 1881-1972; Crane, Josephine Boardman, 1873-1972; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972; Wescott, Glenway, 1901-1987
- Correspondence, 1912-1972; Series I; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by name.
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes correspondence, primarily of a routine personal nature, the bulk of which relates to cultural events hosted by Crane.
  - "A" general, 1934-1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abbott, Jere, 1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Aberconway, Christabel, 1950-1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Acton, Harold, 1950-1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Adams, F. B., Jr., 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Adams, J. Quincy, 1940, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Allen, Hervey, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "B" general, 1930-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Barber, Samuel, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Barzun, Jacques, 1944-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Beddington, Claude, Mrs., 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Berle, Adolf and Beatrice, 1941, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Berman, Eugene, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Blixen, Karen, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Correspondence, guest lists, and arrangements related to 21 January 1959 event in honor of Baroness Blixen. Includes one ALS from Karen Blixen addressed to JBC.
  - Bosworth, Welles, 1957-1964 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Burden-Muller, Rowland, 1958-1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "C" general, 1918-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Canby, Henry S., 1944-1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Caturla, María Luisa, 1945-1956 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Colefax, Sibyl, 1940-1950, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Colum, Mary M., 1940-1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Colum, Padraic, 1927-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Cook, Walter W. S., 1953-1962, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Cooke, Dwight, 1948-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Coolidge, Grace, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Cortissoz, Royal, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Crothers, Rachel, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Cunard, Emerald, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "D" general, 1927-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Dali, Salvador, 1940, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Dewey, John, 1929-1930, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Dinesen, Isak
    Related Archival Materials note
    Series I., Box 1, Folder 14, Blixen, Karen
  - "E" general, 1938-1955 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Ede, H. S., 1939-1965 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Einstein, Lewis, 1950-1963 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Engle, Paul, 1933-1954 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Ervine, St. John, 1928-1929 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - "F" general, 1944-1958 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Faÿ, Bernard, 1927-1955 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Frost, Robert and Lesley, 1947-1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - "G" general, 1922-1961, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Gamson, Arnold U., 1951, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Gogarty, Oliver St. John, 1939-1957, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Golding, Louis, 1928-1942, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Granville-Barker, Harley and Helen, 1944-1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Graves, Robert, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - "H" general, 1928-1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Harrod, Roy, Sir, 1949-1967 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Howard, Isabella, Lady, 1946-1962 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Huxley, Aldous, 1947-1957 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - "I" general, 1949-1956, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - "J" general, 1928-1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - "K" general, 1928-1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Kennedy, William, 1958-1961, undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Kung, H. H. and Madame, 1932-1958 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - "L" general, 1928-1961 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Littlefield, Lester, 1940, undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Lyndon, Andrew, 1955-1966 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - "M" general, 1926-1960 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Masters, Edgar Lee, 1929-1944 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Maurois, André and Simone, 1930-1960, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Menotti, Gian-Carlo, 1937-1954 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Michalopoulos, André, 1945-1960 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Michałowski, Roman, 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Moore, Marianne, 1940-1967 (Box 3, Folder 65-66)
    Includes bills and correspondence related to medical and travel expenses
  - Maugham, W. Somerset, 1942-1953, undated (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - "N" general, 1929-1951, undated (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Newton, Elbert, 1932-1939, undated (Box 4, Folder 69)
    Includes third-party correspondence related to the weekly literature class taught by Newton
  - "O" general, 1955-1960 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Orrick, James B., 1956-1963 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - "P" general, 1915-1963, undated (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Pechkoff, Zinovi, 1949-1956 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Porter, Katherine Anne, 1943-1958 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Priest, Alan, 1942-1965, undated (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Prokosch, Frederic, 1942-1963, undated (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - "R" general, 1927-1963, undated (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Rasponi, Lanfranco, 1940-1972 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Reed, Henry H., Jr., 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Ridge, Lola, 1928-1931 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Roberts, Cecil, 1940-1963 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - "S" general, 1927-1962 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Sandoz, Maurice, 1945-1958 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Sforza, Count, 1937, undated (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Shih, Hu, 1927-1958 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Sitwell, Edith, 1948-1956, undated (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Sitwell, Osbert, 1949-1957 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Snow, Charles P., Sir, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 88)
    Correspondence, guest lists, and arrangements related to C. P. Snow speaking engagement, 8 December 1960. Includes two TLS from C. P. Snow addressed to JBC.
  - Spender, Stephen, 1947-1949, undated (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Starkie, Walter, 1929-1961 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Stein, Gertrude, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Stephens, James, undated (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Stokes, Muriel, 1951-1959 (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Storrs, Ronald, Sir, 1939-1954 (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Stringfield, Lamar, 1929-1930, undated (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - "T" general, 1935-1959, undated (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Taft, William Howard, 1912, undated (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - Thomas, Norman, 1957-1967 (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Thomson, Virgil, 1939-1959 (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - Toklas, Alice B., 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - "V" general, 1961, undated (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - "W" general, 1927-1965, undated (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - Wescott, Glenway, 1937-1963 (Box 5, Folder 103-104)
  - Wheeler, Monroe, 1944-1963, undated (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - White, Newman, 1939-1945 (Box 5, Folder 106)
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1930-1955 (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - Williams, Stanley T., 1925 (Box 5, Folder 108)
  - Wind, Edgar and Margaret, 1942-1963 (Box 5, Folder 109)
  - Young, Stark, 1945-1948, undated (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - Zabel, Morton D., 1960 (Box 5, Folder 111)
- Diaries, 1926-1963; Series II; (13 boxes)
  Prior to the 1977 gift, typescripts of the diaries were produced under the direction of Louise Crane.
  Diaries and transcripts are integrated and arranged chronologically. In some instances, due to space limitations, a corresponding typescript will be housed in the next consecutive box. The full run of diaries and transcripts is followed by three boxes of use copies of the diary transcripts.
  - Diaries and transcripts, 1924-1943 (Box 6, Folder 112-117)
    5 volumes (1924-1943), 1 transcript (1926-1933)
    Crane's diary dated January 1934 to December 1943, differs from the preceding and successive volumes in that it is typewritten and spiral bound and exclusively documents events in terms of guest lists and menus. There is no transcript for this volume.
    There is a handwritten diary for 1943, which documents Crane's routine experiences. The transcript for this volume follows in the next box.
  - Diaries and transcripts, 1943-1945 (Box 7, Folder 118-122)
    2 volumes (1944-1945), 3 transcripts (1943-1945)
  - Diaries and transcripts, 1946-1948 (Box 8, Folder 123-127)
    3 volumes (1946-1948), 2 transcripts (1946-1947)
  - Diaries and transcripts, 1948-1950 (Box 9, Folder 128-132)
    3 volumes (1949-1950), 2 transcripts (1948-1949)
  - Diaries and transcripts, 1950-1952 (Box 10, Folder 133-136)
    2 volumes (1951-1952), 2 transcripts (1950-1951)
  - Diaries and transcripts, 1952-1954 (Box 11, Folder 137-140)
    2 volumes (1953-1954), 2 transcripts (1952-1953)
  - Diaries and transcripts, 1954-1956 (Box 12, Folder 141-145)
    2 volumes (1955-1956), 3 transcripts (1954-1956)
  - Diaries and transcripts, 1957-1959 (Box 13, Folder 146-150)
    3 volumes (1957-1959), 2 transcripts (1957-1958)
  - Diaries and transcripts, 1959-1962 (Box 14, Folder 151-156)
    3 volumes (1960-1962), transcripts (1959-1961)
  - Diaries and transcripts, 1962-1963 (Box 15, Folder 157-159)
    1 volume (1963), 2 transcripts (1962-1963)
  - Diary transcripts (use copies), 1926-1948 (Box 16, Folder 160-166)
  - Diary transcripts (use copies), 1949-1955 (Box 17, Folder 167-173)
  - Diary transcripts (use copies), 1956-1963 (Box 18, Folder 174-181)
- Event files and personal papers, 1920-1964; Series III; (2 boxes)
  - Event files, 1942-1960
    The series includes materials related to social and cultural events given and sponsored by Crane, including guest lists, correspondence, menus, invitations, lecture notes and scripts
    - Discussions and musicales
      - General, 1942-1956 (Box 19, Folder 182-188)
      - Robert Graves (speaker), February 10, 1958 (Box 19, Folder 189)
      - Salvador de Madariaga (speaker), April 16, 1959 (Box 19, Folder 190)
      - Music: Frances Poulenc and Denise Duval, March 15, 1960 (Box 19, Folder 191)
    - Journals, 1936-1945 (Box 19, Folder 192)
    - Menus, 1941-1943, undated (Box 19, Folder 193)
    - Miscellaneous guest lists, 1929-1955, undated (Box 19, Folder 194-195)
    - Miscellaneous invitations, undated (Box 20, Folder 196)
      Autograph and printed outgoing invitations
    - Programs, 1925-1956 (Box 20, Folder 197-199)
      Includes performances by Paul Robeson and Lawrence Brown, the Renaissance Chamber Orchestra, and numerous events sponsored by the American Chamber Opera Society
    - Scripts
      - W. B. Yeats, "The Words upon the Window Pane", undated (Box 20, Folder 200)
        Annotated typescripts and cast list
      - Miscellaneous performances, undated (Box 20, Folder 201)
  - Personal papers, 1920-1964, undated
    - Book notes, 1920-1942 (Box 20, Folder 202)
      Journal including notes, clippings, and recipes
    - Political interests, 1932-1944 (Box 20, Folder 203)
      Contributions and correspondence
    - Travel, 1934 (Box 20, Folder 204)
      Materials related to a trip to Mexico
    - Miscellaneous notes and clippings, 1923-1964, undated (Box 20, Folder 205)
      Includes an envelope of material designated "for scrapbook"